<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
  <title>speedie // based posts</title> 
  <link>https://spdgmr.github.io/posts</link>
  <description>Mostly Linux opinions and random opinions.></description>
<atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/spdgmr/posts/main/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
  <item>
    <title>Stop making Linux user friendly.. sort of</title>
    <link>https://spdgmr.github.io/post01</link>
    <guid>https://spdgmr.github.io/post01</guid>
    <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>Wanted to state my opinion on a problem that's getting bigger and bigger. A problem that's getting bigger with each day is that we're making technology easier but it's also getting more and more "evil" with big tech companies (FAANG for example) collecting and selling our data for monetary gain. </p>
    <p>So then we turn to alternatives (Usually free software and Linux) which is a good thing, more people caring about their online privacy. </p>
    <p>The problem is how we approach these new users. We want it to be easy for them but in the process of making it easy for new users we're also making it a nightmare for experienced users and slowly making Linux just as bloated as those proprietary operating systems. </p>
    <p>What do I mean with "bloat" since that term is kind of a meme by now? </p>
    <p>Nowdays most of the software we use is bloated. The websites you visit likely have a lot of JavaScript in them (Facebook, Google, Discord, Instagram, Twitter, etc.) which forces us to have bloated web browsers for viewing those pages slowing down older computers. Additionally this also requires a GUI program which some users might not want. </p>
    <p>But even if you avoid the web there's still bloat in a lot of software. A lot of software on Linux now is packaged using Universal packaging like Snap packages (Canonical), Flatpaks (Red Hat), and AppImages (some random idiot).</p>
    <p>Now since soydevs decide to package using these and since these are universal, every single package has </p>
    <p>-to have support for every distro which obviously is very bloated and probably moreso than .dmgs containing a binary on macOS or a .exe since there are more Linux distros than macOS versions/Windows versions. </p> 
    <p>Thing is, when you're trying to keep your system minimal for multiple reasons (Could be old hardware or </p> 
    <p>you simply like minimal software) these packages are just not an option. You might say, "Just compile from source" (as if I'm not already using Portage) </p> 
    <p>And yes, I can definitely see your point but the problem comes when software is *absolutely proprietary*, because you can't exactly compile software without the source code in your hands. </p> 
    <p>Now proprietary software is NOT minimal, obviously however whenever you need to install a piece of proprietary software you may in some cases be forced to use one of these bloated packages since the proprietary software developer is too lazy to actually use the distro specific package managers or AT LEAST provide a tarball for the user. </p> 
    <p>So what are these universal package formats good for? Well, they're good for Windows/macOS normies who are used to things *just-working* without any tinkering. But problem comes when everyone starts adopting-</p> 
    <p>this new fancy packaging format. Because once these become standard (I definitely predict they will), you will be forced to use them (unless the software is free and open source). </p>
    <p>TLDR; By using bloated universal packages and making it easy for the normies, you're making it harder for minimal Linux users/experienced users who REALLY hate universal packaging. </p> 
    <p>So please, if you're going to distribute software, PLEASE PLEASE PLEASE provide packaging for the distro's native package manager (Apt for Debian/Ubuntu, Pacman for Arch, Rpm for Red Hat, Portage for Gentoo, XBPS for Void, etc.). </p> 
    <p>Thank you and have a good day</p>]]>
    </description>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>NOTE for spDE users</title>
    <link>https://spdgmr.github.io/post02</link>
    <guid>https://spdgmr.github.io/post02</guid>
    <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>This is a notice for spDE users. It now comes with newsboat and this RSS feed built in. There may or may not be a keybind but you can access it from the terminal by running 'newsboat'.</p> 
    <p>Thank you for using spDE.</p>]]>
    </description>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Dear soydevs: Stop making desktop applications bloated.</title>
    <link>https://spdgmr.github.io/post03</link>
    <guid>https://spdgmr.github.io/post03</guid>
    <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>Today I wanted to talk about something else. I guess it's kinda related to my previous post titled "Stop making Linux user friendly.. sort of".</p>
    <p>Modern software has this problem, a very huge problem. "Bloat". Now bloat can be caused by many different aspects. Programming language, po-</p>
    <p>orly written code, unnecessary features, etc. but the main one I wanna talk about is called "Electron".</p>
    <p>Now if you're not familiar with Electron, it's basically a minimal version of Chromium designed to create individual desktop applications from</p>
    <p>HTML, CSS and JavaScript. This makes it easy to create desktop applications as long as you know a lot about web development.</p>
    <p>In fact many desktop applications you might be using (Almost all of them are proprietary) use Electron.</p>
    <p>Examples of these are: GitHub Desktop, balenaEtcher, Discord, Spotify, and yes, even a text editor, Visual Studio Code or as I like to call it, "SoyDev Code".</p>
    <p>If you've viewed my page, https://spdgmr.github.io/hate, you'll know that both Electron and the JavaScript programming language is there on my list.</p>
    <p>Either way, JavaScript is a VERY bloated language and is often obfuscated making it harder to see spyware, even if it's TECHNICALLY open source.</p>
    <p>Now JavaScript is becoming more popular in web development and this fact is pissing people who want a minimal system off.</p>
    <p>So to make it worse, since Electron allows you to turn HTML+CSS+JS into a desktop application, this means JS will be used for software as well.</p>
    <p>You might say, "I have a fast computer so I don't care if the software is bloated or not" and while that's a fair point, what if someone doesn't have a fast computer or just simply l-</p>
    <p> ikes minimal software. Then they're essentially forced to use this bloated slow application just because a developer was too lazy to actually learn another language.</p>
    <p>TLDR; The web is extremely bloated and since Electron turns "the web" into a desktop application, software on the desktop is getting bloated too.</p>
    <p>So what do I want? I want developers to STOP using this Electron trash.</p>
    <p>Thank you and have a good day!</p>
    ]]>
    </description>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>What you can expect from Project 081 0.6</title>
    <link>https://spdgmr.github.io/post04</link>
    <guid>https://spdgmr.github.io/post04</guid>
    <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>This is an update for Project 081 users (if there still are any). As this project has slowly died I would like to finally finish it as I have been</p>
    <p>working on other stuff like gentoo-install, spDE, my RSS feed, sfetch and various other projects.</p>
    <p>After I spent more time with Linux and stuff my older Mac OS X project kinda.. died. So therefore my goal is to finish Project 081 soon so that</p>
    <p>it's as good as it can possibly be. All the assets are (hopefully) complete however it has yet to be "compiled" together into an image for the user.</p>
    <p>So while you wait, here's a list of a bunch of changes i've made to Project 081 as well as a few I'm going to do.</p>
    <p>- Project 081 0.6/1.0 now comes with sfetch</p>
    <p>- Project 081 0.6/1.0 might come with an RSS reader as well as my feed.</p>
    <p>- Project 081 0.6/1.0 will FINALLY fix AirPort for iMac8,1 users.</p>
    <p>- Project 081 0.6/1.0 will hopefully boot on all systems.</p>
    <p>- Project 081 0.6/1.0 will hopefully be a single image with a single package that determines what to install based on sysctl hw.model</p>
    <p>- Project 081 0.6/1.0 will be an even smaller image</p>
    <p>- Project 081 0.6/1.0 will have a preinstalled image available.</p>
    <p>- Project 081 0.6/1.0 will FINALLY come with drivers for newer Apple keyboards</p>
    <p>That's basically what you can expect, if you have any more suggestions please create an Issue on GitHub.</p>
    <p>That's all, Have a good day!</p>]]>
    </description>
  </item>
  <item>
	<title>Happy 20th Birthday Arch Linux!</title>
	<link>https://spdgmr.github.io/post05</link>
	<guid>https://spdgmr.github.io/post05</guid>
	<pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
	<description>
	<![CDATA[<p>So today, 2022-03-11 depending on your time zone marks 20 years since Arch Linux was released to the public.</p>
	<p>I would like to show some respect by creating this very post. Arch Linux is still one of the best Linux distributions today and I use it on a few machines.</p>
	<p>Even though I personally use Gentoo, Arch Linux was what got me into minimal Linux distributions and bloat-free software so I believe we should give it the respect it deserves.</p>
	<p>So thank you Arch Linux for being "different" and being minimal. Although I don't agree with some of your decisions such as switching from OpenRC to Systemd, you're one of the most popular distros and managed to get many people away from the bloated</p>
	<p>Linux distributions to something minimal and DIY. You even basically created Linux elitism by making an OS</p>
	<p>that's difficult to install. Happy 20th Birthday Arch Linux and thank you for reading this.</p>]]>
	</description>
  </item>
  <item>
	<title>It's time to stop using Adblock Plus (seriously stop)</title>
	<link>https://spdgmr.github.io/post06</link>
	<guid>https://spdgmr.github.io/post06</guid>
	<pubDate>Sat, 12 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
	<description>
	<![CDATA[<p>One of the most popular types of browser extensions have been ad blockers.</p>
	<p>Now there are so many ad blockers, most of them being absolutely terrible that it can be hard to pick one.</p>
	<p>But fear not, just look for the highest rated one right? Well.. No. Because on most browsers Adblock Plus is the highest</p>
	<p> rated extension and therefgore it's also the most popular. </p> <p>But little do most users know that ABP isn't what it seems. You see, big tech companies pay the creator(s) of ABP to not block their ads.</p>
	<p>You might say, these are what ABP calls "Acceptable Ads" but NO, these are not just whitelisted until you manually disable them, these are ALWAYS whitelisted.</p>
	<p>Now, let's talk about what "Acceptable Ads" are. These are ads that ABP deems "Acceptable" and they likely get paid to make these "Acceptable". </p> <p>The reason this feature exists is obvious. Most normies don't spent time "tinkering" with their software and therefore probably use the default settings.</p>
	<p>And "Acceptable Ads" are also enabled by default. So the user installs ABP thinking they're getting privacy and an ad free experience when that's not really the case.</p>
	<p>Guess what makes it worse? ABP doesn't tell its users that they're being paid money by big tech companies. And because ABP is one of the most popular if not THE most popular ad blocker its users are going to trust it no matter what. </p> <p>So what ad blocker should you use? Well, you could go with the least bloated option which is to edit your /etc/hosts file but manually adding entries is extremely time consuming and ultimately not worth your time so instead you can simply use the "uBlock Origin" extension which is available for Chromium, WebKit and Firefox based browsers. </p>
	<p>uBlock Origin despite having a bad name in my opinion is definitely the best ad blocker. It's 100% open source and free as in freedom. Its filter is also public and if you really want you can add it to your /etc/hosts manually. It has no "Acceptable Ads" trash which means money doesn't decide what's going to be blocked. </p>
	<p>It also has a bunch of other nice features that other ad blockers lack such as preventing WebRTC leaks and disabling JavaScript, cookies, trackers and other stuff that you might not want. It's definitely one of the best browser extensions and I highly recommend it. </p>]]>
	</description>
  </item>
  <item>
	<title>rchat 0.4 is here (Now available on Arch and Gentoo)</title>
	<link>https://spdgmr.github.io/post07</link>
	<guid>https://spdgmr.github.io/post07</guid>
	<pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
	<description>
	<![CDATA[<p>rchat 0.4 has finally been released. This release doesn't bring much of note except a few commands.</p>
	<p>However, you can now install rchat easily on Arch Linux through the AUR and Gentoo using my ebuild repository.</p>
	<p>To install rchat 0.4 on Gentoo, add my overlay, you can find out how to do so by following this link: https://github.com/spoverlay/splay.</p>
	<p>To install rchat 0.4 on Arch, simply install the AUR package. You can use an AUR helper like 'yay' if you want. Usage with 'yay' is 'yay -S rchat'.</p>
	<p>For other GNU/Linux distributions, you can head over to my GitHub and download the latest version. Or clone it using Git.</p>
	<p>The latest release can be found here. Simply download, save to /usr/bin/rchat and chmod +x /usr/bin/rchat.</p>
 	<p>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/speediegamer/rchat/main/rchat</p>]]> 
	</description>
  </item>
  <item>
	<title>Facecucks BTFO by rchat 0.5 (rchat 0.5 is here)</title>
	<link>https://spdgmr.github.io/post08</link>
	<guid>https://spdgmr.github.io/post08</guid>
	<pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
	<description>
	<![CDATA[<p>rchat 0.5 is here. It brings a few more commands such as setting how quickly messages are loaded.</p>
	<p>It is likely one of the last feature updates, as new features will come in the form of patches.</p>
	<p>rchat now has it's own page on my website, you can check it out here: https://speedie.gq/rchat.html</p>
        <p>In addition to this, patches are now available. At the time of making this post, there's a .Xresources patch available for 0.5</p>
	<p>Please be respectful and don't abuse the new feature.</p>
        <p>- To install rchat 0.5 on Gentoo, add my overlay, you can find out how to do so by following this link: https://github.com/spoverlay/splay.</p>
	<p>- To install rchat 0.5 on Arch, simply install the AUR package. You can use an AUR helper like 'yay' if you want. Usage with 'yay' is 'yay -S rchat'.</p>
	<p>- For other GNU/Linux distributions, you can head over to my GitHub and download the latest version. Or clone it using Git.</p>
	<p>The latest release can be found here. Simply download, save to /usr/bin/rchat and chmod +x /usr/bin/rchat.</p>
        <p>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/speediegamer/rchat/main/rchat</p>
	<p>- speedie</p>]]>
	</description>
 </item>
 <item>
	<title>Everything I want to use is Chromium</title>
	<link>https://spdgmr.github.io/post09</link>
	<guid>https://spdgmr.github.io/post09</guid>
	<pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
	<description>
	<![CDATA[<p>Good morning/evening/night gigachads. Today I wanted to speak about a problem. As you've probably read from the title which is 'Everything I want to use is Chromium', everything I want to use is Chromium.</p>
	<p>No matter if you like Chromium or hate Chromium, it is a problem because centralization is a problem. In this case, centralization refers to a product with a marketshare so far above everything else, it's slowly killing any and all alternatives. </p>
	<p>Back in the day, There were really only two web engines; Trident or whatever it was called (IE), and Gecko (Netscape/Firefox). This used to be a problem in the late 90s and early 2000s because Internet Explorer was about as dominant as Chromium is today. However as the mid 2000s came around, it was fairly balanced and you could get by with either web browser.</p>
        <p>In 2008, a brand new "fancy" web browser came around called Google Chrome. Little did we know back then but this web browser would later end up essentially destroying the internet. Not the web browser itself, although it's pretty terrible and normies tend to use it, but rather the web engine it had, named 'Chromium'. Now Chromium is based on another web engine called WebKit. The problem is that Chromium is controlled by a big tech company and even worse, a big tech company with advertising as their main goal.</p>
	<p>Now, Chromium is a free software project but since Google, the evil advertising company has the final say about what goes into the project and not, it's not something you should depend on. Chromium ended up being (and still is) the fastest web engine. This led to new websites relying more and more on Chromium. And as the result of that, most web browsers created nowdays are based on the Chromium engine.</p>
        <p>Slowly, Chromium gained massive marketshare and fast forward to today, it's by far the most popular web engine out there. Essentially what we've done is given Google the power over all of our free software projects.</p>
	<p>Not only that but with massive marketshare came web centralization. Google, the evil company has a monopoly on advertising, hosting and video sharing and even web searching. Who is to say they won't use their monopoly and power for evil in the "free software" project Chromium which is in most web browsers today?</p>
	<p>Mozilla, the creators of Firefox and other free-software projects like Thunderbird don't have advertising in mind and rather try to encourage a free and open source web. However due to bad decisions and Gecko being slow, Chromium has taken over and now Mozilla is really struggling to keep the Firefox project going.</p>
	<p>You might say, "just fork Gecko" and while that would be valid, Gecko is REALLY difficult to work with and that's the problem. You can't just easily create a browser based on Gecko because it's too difficult and time consuming. </p>
        <p>Now, I'm not gonna go too in depth on this but many DESKTOP applications are also becoming Chromium. The reason is that soydevs have essentially stopped making regular Desktop applications and are instead using something called 'Electron'. Electron is basically a minimal (but still EXTREMELY bloated Chromium) which is even worse because even if you avoid Chromium for your web browser by using a Firefox based browser like GNU/Icecat, Tor, Firefox, Waterfox, Librewolf, etc. you'll still have Chromium based applications on your system.</p>
	<p>It's getting really common. balenaEtcher, Discord, Spotify, Telegram, etc. desktop clients are all using Electron/Chromium.</p>
	<p>So what do I want? I want a decentralized web. To support this, we need to somehow grow Firefox and Webkit based browsers' marketshare so that the marketshare is more even. So that, if Google eventually destroys Chromium and makes it a spyware monopoly, we have another engine to fall back on.</p>
        <p>A good way to do this would be to bring back the old 'Choose a browser' prompt Microsoft was forced to show every time Internet Explorer was launched on Windows 7 and 8.</p>
        <p>To contribute to this, I've decided to BAN myself from ever touching anything based on Chromium or Electron. Chromium might be great, or it might suck but I refuse to support a bloated, centralized web. If you wanna support a decentralized web, I suggest you do the same.</p>
	<p> - speedie</p>]]>
        </description>
 </item>
</channel>
</rss>
