<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
  <title>speedie // based posts</title> 
  <link>https://speedie.gq/blog</link>
  <description>speedie's super based blog.></description>
<atom:link href="https://speedie.gq/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
  <item>
    <title>Stop making GNU/Linux user friendly.. sort of</title>
    <link>https://speedie.gq/post01.html</link>
    <guid>https://speedie.gq/post01.html</guid>
    <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>A problem that's getting bigger with each day is that we're making technology easier but it's also getting more and more "evil" with big tech companies collecting and selling our data for monetary gain. </p>
    <p>So then we turn to alternatives (Usually free software and GNU/Linux) which is a good thing, more people caring about their online privacy. </p>
    <p>The problem is how we approach these new users. We want it to be easy for them but in the process of making it easy for new users we're also making it a nightmare for experienced users and slowly making GNU/Linux just as bloated as those proprietary operating systems. </p>
    <p>What do I mean with "bloat" since that term is kind of a meme by now? </p>
    <p>Nowdays most of the software we use is bloated. The websites you visit likely have a lot of JavaScript in them (Facebook, Google, Discord, Instagram, Twitter, etc.) which forces us to have bloated web browsers for viewing those pages slowing down older computers. Additionally this also requires a GUI program which some users might not want. </p>
    <p>But even if you avoid the web there's still bloat in a lot of software. A lot of software on GNU/Linux now is packaged using Universal packaging like Snap packages (Canonical), Flatpaks (Red Hat), and AppImages (some random idiot).</p>
    <p>Now since soydevs decide to package using these and since these are universal, every single package has </p>
    <p>-to have support for every distro which obviously is very bloated and probably moreso than .dmgs containing a binary on macOS or a .exe since there are more GNU/Linux distros than macOS versions/Windows versions. </p> 
    <p>Thing is, when you're trying to keep your system minimal for multiple reasons (Could be old hardware or </p> 
    <p>you simply like minimal software) these packages are just not an option. You might say, "Just compile from source" (as if I'm not already using Portage) </p> 
    <p>And yes, I can definitely see your point but the problem comes when software is *absolutely proprietary*, because you can't exactly compile software without the source code in your hands. </p> 
    <p>Now proprietary software is NOT minimal, obviously however whenever you need to install a piece of proprietary software you may in some cases be forced to use one of these bloated packages since the proprietary software developer is too lazy to actually use the distro specific package managers or AT LEAST provide a tarball for the user. </p> 
    <p>So what are these universal package formats good for? Well, they're good for Windows/macOS normies who are used to things <i>just-working</i> without any tinkering. But problem comes when everyone starts adopting-</p> 
    <p>this new fancy packaging format. Because once these become standard (I definitely predict they will), you will be forced to use them (unless the software is free and open source). And even then, you may be forced to compile it from source yourself if you want to reject universal packages. </p>
    <p>TLDR; By using bloated universal packages and making it easy for the normies, you're making it harder for minimal GNU/Linux users/experienced users who REALLY hate universal packaging. </p> 
    <p>So please, if you're going to distribute software, please provide packaging for the distro's native package manager.</p> 
    <p>Have a good day!</p>]]>
    </description>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>NOTE for spDE users</title>
    <link>https://speedie.gq/post02.html</link>
    <guid>https://speedie.gq/post02.html</guid>
    <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>This is a notice for spDE users. It now comes with newsboat and this RSS feed built in. There may or may not be a keybind but you can access it from the terminal by running 'newsboat'.</p> 
    <p>Thank you for using spDE.</p>]]>
    </description>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Dear soydevs: Stop making desktop applications bloated.</title>
    <link>https://speedie.gq/post03.html</link>
    <guid>https://speedie.gq/post03.html</guid>
    <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>Today I wanted to talk about something else. I guess it's kinda related to my previous post titled "Stop making GNU/Linux user friendly.. sort of".</p>
    <p>Modern software has this problem, a very huge problem. "Bloat". Now bloat can be caused by many different aspects. Programming language, po-</p>
    <p>orly written code, unnecessary features, etc. but the main one I wanna talk about is called "Electron".</p>
    <p>Now if you're not familiar with Electron, it's basically a minimal version of Chromium designed to create individual desktop applications from</p>
    <p>HTML, CSS and JavaScript. This makes it easy to create desktop applications as long as you know a lot about web development.</p>
    <p>In fact many desktop applications you might be using (Almost all of them are proprietary) use Electron.</p>
    <p>Examples of these are: GitHub Desktop, balenaEtcher, Discord, Spotify, and yes, even a text editor, Visual Studio Code or as I like to call it, "SoyDev Code".</p>
    <p>Either way, JavaScript is a VERY bloated language and is often obfuscated making it harder to see spyware, even if it's TECHNICALLY open source.</p>
    <p>Now JavaScript is becoming more popular in web development and this fact is pissing people who want a minimal system off.</p>
    <p>So to make it worse, since Electron allows you to turn HTML+CSS+JS into a desktop application, this means JS will be used for software as well.</p>
    <p>You might say, "I have a fast computer so I don't care if the software is bloated or not" and while that's a fair point, what if someone doesn't have a fast computer or just simply likes- </p>
    <p>minimal software. Then they're essentially forced to use this bloated slow application just because a developer was too lazy to actually learn another language.</p>
    <p>TLDR; The web is extremely bloated and since Electron turns "the web" into a desktop application, software on the desktop is getting bloated too.</p>
    <p>So what do I want? I want developers to STOP using this Electron trash. It really is not difficult to create a nice desktop application.</p>
    <p>Thank you and have a good day!</p>]]>
    </description>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>What you can expect from Project 081 0.6</title>
    <link>https://speedie.gq/post04.html</link>
    <guid>https://speedie.gq/post04.html</guid>
    <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <description>
    <![CDATA[<p>This is an update for Project 081 users (if there still are any). As this project has slowly died I would like to finally finish it as I have been</p>
    <p>working on other stuff like gentoo-install, spDE, my RSS feed, sfetch and various other projects.</p>
    <p>After I spent more time with Linux and stuff my older Mac OS X project kinda.. died. So therefore my goal is to finish Project 081 soon so that</p>
    <p>it's as good as it can possibly be. All the assets are (hopefully) complete however it has yet to be "compiled" together into an image for the user.</p>
    <p>So while you wait, here's a list of a bunch of changes i've made to Project 081 as well as a few I'm going to do.</p>
    <p>- Project 081 0.6/1.0 now comes with sfetch</p>
    <p>- Project 081 0.6/1.0 might come with an RSS reader as well as my feed.</p>
    <p>- Project 081 0.6/1.0 will FINALLY fix AirPort for iMac8,1 users.</p>
    <p>- Project 081 0.6/1.0 will hopefully boot on all systems.</p>
    <p>- Project 081 0.6/1.0 will hopefully be a single image with a single package that determines what to install based on sysctl hw.model</p>
    <p>- Project 081 0.6/1.0 will be an even smaller image</p>
    <p>- Project 081 0.6/1.0 will have a preinstalled image available.</p>
    <p>- Project 081 0.6/1.0 will FINALLY come with drivers for newer Apple keyboards</p>
    <p>That's basically what you can expect, if you have any more suggestions please create an Issue on GitHub.</p>
    <p>That's all, Have a good day!</p>]]>
    </description>
  </item>
  <item>
	<title>Happy 20th Birthday Arch Linux!</title>
	<link>https://speedie.gq/post05.html</link>
	<guid>https://speedie.gq/post05.html</guid>
	<pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
	<description>
	<![CDATA[<p>So today, 2022-03-11 depending on your time zone marks 20 years since Arch Linux was released to the public.</p>
	<p>I would like to show some respect by creating this very post. Arch Linux is still one of the best Linux distributions today and I use it on a few machines.</p>
	<p>Even though I personally use Gentoo, Arch Linux was what got me into minimal Linux distributions and bloat-free software so I believe we should give it the respect it deserves.</p>
	<p>So thank you Arch Linux for being "different" and being minimal. Although I don't agree with some of your decisions such as switching from OpenRC to Systemd, you're one of the most popular distros and managed to get many people away from the bloated</p>
	<p>Linux distributions to something minimal and DIY. You even basically created Linux elitism by making an OS</p>
	<p>that's difficult to install. Happy 20th Birthday Arch Linux and thank you for reading this.</p>]]>
	</description>
  </item>
  <item>
	<title>It's time to stop using Adblock Plus (seriously stop)</title>
	<link>https://speedie.gq/post06.html</link>
	<guid>https://speedie.gq/post06.html</guid>
	<pubDate>Sat, 12 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
	<description>
	<![CDATA[<p>One of the most popular types of browser extensions have been ad blockers.</p>
	<p>Now there are so many ad blockers, most of them being absolutely terrible that it can be hard to pick one.</p>
	<p>But fear not, just look for the highest rated one right? Well.. No. Because on most browsers Adblock Plus is the highest</p>
	<p> rated extension and therefgore it's also the most popular. </p> <p>But little do most users know that ABP isn't what it seems. You see, big tech companies pay the creator(s) of ABP to not block their ads.</p>
	<p>You might say, these are what ABP calls "Acceptable Ads" but NO, these are not just whitelisted until you manually disable them, these are ALWAYS whitelisted.</p>
	<p>Now, let's talk about what "Acceptable Ads" are. These are ads that ABP deems "Acceptable" and they likely get paid to make these "Acceptable". </p> <p>The reason this feature exists is obvious. Most normies don't spent time "tinkering" with their software and therefore probably use the default settings.</p>
	<p>And "Acceptable Ads" are also enabled by default. So the user installs ABP thinking they're getting privacy and an ad free experience when that's not really the case.</p>
	<p>Guess what makes it worse? ABP doesn't tell its users that they're being paid money by big tech companies. And because ABP is one of the most popular if not THE most popular ad blocker its users are going to trust it no matter what. </p> <p>So what ad blocker should you use? Well, you could go with the least bloated option which is to edit your /etc/hosts file but manually adding entries is extremely time consuming and ultimately not worth your time so instead you can simply use the "uBlock Origin" extension which is available for Chromium, WebKit and Firefox based browsers. </p>
	<p>uBlock Origin despite having a bad name in my opinion is definitely the best ad blocker. It's 100% open source and free as in freedom. Its filter is also public and if you really want you can add it to your /etc/hosts manually. It has no "Acceptable Ads" trash which means money doesn't decide what's going to be blocked. </p>
	<p>It also has a bunch of other nice features that other ad blockers lack such as preventing WebRTC leaks and disabling JavaScript, cookies, trackers and other stuff that you might not want. It's definitely one of the best browser extensions and I highly recommend it. </p>]]>
	</description>
  </item>
  <item>
	<title>rchat 0.4 is here (Now available on Arch and Gentoo)</title>
	<link>https://speedie.gq/post07.html</link>
	<guid>https://speedie.gq/post07.html</guid>
	<pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
	<description>
	<![CDATA[<p>rchat 0.4 has finally been released. This release doesn't bring much of note except a few commands.</p>
	<p>However, you can now install rchat easily on Arch Linux through the AUR and Gentoo using my ebuild repository.</p>
	<p>To install rchat 0.4 on Gentoo, add my overlay, you can find out how to do so by following this link: https://github.com/spoverlay/splay.</p>
	<p>To install rchat 0.4 on Arch, simply install the AUR package. You can use an AUR helper like 'yay' if you want. Usage with 'yay' is 'yay -S rchat'.</p>
	<p>For other GNU/Linux distributions, you can head over to my GitHub and download the latest version. Or clone it using Git.</p>
	<p>The latest release can be found here. Simply download, save to /usr/bin/rchat and chmod +x /usr/bin/rchat.</p>
 	<p>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/speediegq/rchat/main/rchat</p>]]> 
	</description>
  </item>
  <item>
	<title>Half an rchat (rchat 0.5 is out)</title>
	<link>https://speedie.gq/post08.html</link>
	<guid>https://speedie.gq/post08.html</guid>
	<pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
	<description>
	<![CDATA[<p>rchat 0.5 is here. It brings a few more commands such as setting how quickly messages are loaded.</p>
	<p>It is likely one of the last feature updates, as new features will come in the form of patches.</p>
	<p>rchat now has it's own page on my website, you can check it out here: https://speedie.gq/rchat.html</p>
        <p>In addition to this, patches are now available. At the time of making this post, there's a .Xresources patch available for 0.5</p>
	<p>Please be respectful and don't abuse the new feature.</p>
        <p>- To install rchat 0.5 on Gentoo, add my overlay, you can find out how to do so by following this link: https://github.com/spoverlay/splay.</p>
	<p>- To install rchat 0.5 on Arch, simply install the AUR package. You can use an AUR helper like 'yay' if you want. Usage with 'yay' is 'yay -S rchat'.</p>
	<p>- For other GNU/Linux distributions, you can head over to my GitHub and download the latest version. Or clone it using Git.</p>
	<p>The latest release can be found here. Simply download, save to /usr/bin/rchat and chmod +x /usr/bin/rchat.</p>
        <p>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/speediegq/rchat/main/rchat</p>
	<p>- speedie</p>]]>
	</description>
 </item>
 <item>
	<title>Everything I want to use is Chromium</title>
	<link>https://speedie.gq/post09.html</link>
	<guid>https://speedie.gq/post09.html</guid>
	<pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
	<description>
	<![CDATA[<p>Good morning/evening/night gigachads. Today I wanted to speak about a problem. As you've probably read from the title which is 'Everything I want to use is Chromium', everything I want to use is Chromium.</p>
	<p>No matter if you like Chromium or hate Chromium, it is a problem because centralization is a problem. In this case, centralization refers to a product with a marketshare so far above everything else, it's slowly killing any and all alternatives. </p>
	<p>Back in the day, There were really only two web engines; Trident or whatever it was called (IE), and Gecko (Netscape/Firefox). This used to be a problem in the late 90s and early 2000s because Internet Explorer was about as dominant as Chromium is today. However as the mid 2000s came around, it was fairly balanced and you could get by with either web browser.</p>
        <p>In 2008, a brand new "fancy" web browser came around called Google Chrome. Little did we know back then but this web browser would later end up essentially destroying the internet. Not the web browser itself, although it's pretty terrible and normies tend to use it, but rather the web engine it had, named 'Chromium'. Now Chromium is based on another web engine called WebKit. The problem is that Chromium is controlled by a big tech company and even worse, a big tech company with advertising as their main goal.</p>
	<p>Now, Chromium is a free software project but since Google, the evil advertising company has the final say about what goes into the project and not, it's not something you should depend on. Chromium ended up being (and still is) the fastest web engine. This led to new websites relying more and more on Chromium. And as the result of that, most web browsers created nowdays are based on the Chromium engine.</p>
        <p>Slowly, Chromium gained massive marketshare and fast forward to today, it's by far the most popular web engine out there. Essentially what we've done is given Google the power over all of our free software projects.</p>
	<p>Not only that but with massive marketshare came web centralization. Google, the evil company has a monopoly on advertising, hosting and video sharing and even web searching. Who is to say they won't use their monopoly and power for evil in the "free software" project Chromium which is in most web browsers today?</p>
	<p>Mozilla, the creators of Firefox and other free-software projects like Thunderbird don't have advertising in mind and rather try to encourage a free and open source web. However due to bad decisions and Gecko being slow, Chromium has taken over and now Mozilla is really struggling to keep the Firefox project going.</p>
	<p>You might say, "just fork Gecko" and while that would be valid, Gecko is REALLY difficult to work with and that's the problem. You can't just easily create a browser based on Gecko because it's too difficult and time consuming. </p>
        <p>Now, I'm not gonna go too in depth on this but many DESKTOP applications are also becoming Chromium. The reason is that soydevs have essentially stopped making regular Desktop applications and are instead using something called 'Electron'. Electron is basically a minimal (but still EXTREMELY bloated Chromium) which is even worse because even if you avoid Chromium for your web browser by using a Firefox based browser like GNU/Icecat, Tor, Firefox, Waterfox, Librewolf, etc. you'll still have Chromium based applications on your system.</p>
	<p>It's getting really common. balenaEtcher, Discord, Spotify, Telegram, etc. desktop clients are all using Electron/Chromium.</p>
	<p>So what do I want? I want a decentralized web. To support this, we need to somehow grow Firefox and Webkit based browsers' marketshare so that the marketshare is more even. So that, if Google eventually destroys Chromium and makes it a spyware monopoly, we have another engine to fall back on.</p>
        <p>A good way to do this would be to bring back the old 'Choose a browser' prompt Microsoft was forced to show every time Internet Explorer was launched on Windows 7 and 8.</p>
        <p>To contribute to this, I've decided to BAN myself from ever touching anything based on Chromium or Electron. Chromium might be great, or it might suck but I refuse to support a bloated, centralized web. If you wanna support a decentralized web, I suggest you do the same.</p>
	<p> - speedie</p>]]>
        </description>
 </item>
 <item>
    <title>xinit is bloated.</title>
	<link>https://speedie.gq/post10.html</link>
	<guid>https://speedie.gq/post10.html</guid>
	<pubDate>Sat, 30 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
	<description>
	<![CDATA[<p>Some GNU/Linux users are very serious about maintaining a minimal system. They use software like dwm as their window manager, written in C with very few dependencies (definitely check it out).</p>
	<p>But even then, they keep using a bloated piece of software just to run an X session.</p>
	<p>That program is 'xinit' or 'startx' as some people call it because that's the command you run to start an X session. To me, there is absolutely no reason to keep using such a bloated program when minimal alternatives exist. In fact, it's really easy to switch to a better alternative.</p>
	<p>If you're running Wayland then you can ignore this post/throw that bloat in the trash, it's not for you. For the rest of us Xorg GNU/Linux chads, I'm going to walk you through a simple program called 'sx'. I've known about this program for months but never actually bothered to try it. As I quickly found it months later however, it is REALLY easy to switch over to sx, even on a system that's already fully set up.</p>
	<p>To get started, change directory to wherever you want and 'git clone https://github.com/Earnestly/sx.git'. Now 'cd sx' and run 'make install' as root.</p>
	<p>Now that you've got sx installed, it's time to start using it. If you're not sure how to use it, you can simply check the 'man sx' page.</p>
	<p>To start a server, if your .xinitrc is in ~ then you can probably just run 'sx sh ~/.xinitrc'. You can use the exact same .xinitrc with sx as with xinit. Now, if you've moved your .xinitrc then it's the exact same command, just change the path.</p>
	<p>If your X is configured properly and the .xinitrc is written properly, your window manager should start just like it did with xinit. Now, sx is just 36 SLOC of POSIX compliant shell so if you want you can easily make changes to it.</p>
	<p>Unless you require very specific settings though, which is quite rare you probably don't need to modify it anyway.</p>
	<p>sx does however have a few problems although I've only encountered one with dfmpeg/ffmpeg where it won't record. It's not a huge deal and it's probably just a dfmpeg thing. If it is and I manage to solve it, a new version of dfmpeg should be released soon.</p>
	<p>Either way, sx is really everything you need an 'X starter' to do. Nothing less, nothing more.</p>]]>
	</description>
</item>
<item>
   <title>Smartphones are only smart because you're dumb.</title>
   <link>https://speedie.gq/post11.html</link>
   <guid>https://speedie.gq/post11.html</guid>
   <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
   <description>
   <![CDATA[<p>As a smartphone user;</p>
   <p>Smartphones are evil. They're slowly turning us into braindead robots who only know how to consume but slowly lose the ability to think and to make decisions. They slowly require their smartphones to make decisions because their brains are becoming more and more useless.</p>
   <p>Now, the problem people who understand how technology is bad for them is facing is normies. Normies don't understand how the technology they use affects them and they don't have any clue how it works. All they know is that it gives them a constant dopamine fix.</p>
   <p>"Smart"phones are good for one thing; giving smartphone companies and government agencies all your data and slowly bluepilling everyone who uses them. They're forcing expensive pocket-sized pieces of glass and spyware onto people which are all running only proprietary software which likely will spy on you as is the case with nearly all non-free software.</p>
   <p>"Smart"phones are slowly taking control over YOU and are now starting to "think" for you. This is a problem because it means you're slowly becoming useless, slowly becoming braindead. You are slowly becoming property of the big tech companies who made your device. The software is all proprietary (non-free) which means you have absolutely no idea what's going on.</p>
   <p>You just have to trust tech companies and most people unfortunately do it without actually thinking for themselves. They think big tech companies are out here being nice trying to make the world a futuristic dream or something.</p>
   <p>Now, for many Android devices and certainly Apple's hardware, you can't just replace the proprietary OS and proprietary bootloader with free software. Because they're not gonna allow that. You may be able to run a more free OS but you'll still have non-free software running on the glass and spyware you possibly paid thousands for.</p>
   <p>So you pay them thousands for a phone which can do almost nothing compared to your computer, then they still spy on you and slowly devolve into a braindead robot.</p>
   <p>Smartphones must be stopped before humanity is ruined.</p>]]>
   </description>
</item>
<item>
   <title>I HATE APPLE!!!</title>
   <link>https://speedie.gq/post12.html</link>
   <guid>https://speedie.gq/post12.html</guid>
   <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
   <description>
   <![CDATA[<p>Today I'm starting a new 'series' of blog posts essentially about how certain companies are evil. This one will be about Apple as I'm pretty sure you can tell if you even read the title of the post.</p>
   <p>Before you call me a biased RMS fan who runs a FSF approved distribution, never goes outside, has Stallman posters and hates everything that isn't free software:</p>
   <p>I am far from biased, in fact I used to run macOS as my main desktop operating system, used an iPad years ago and since 2020, have been maintaining a Mac OS X 10.4 retro project.</p>
   <p>Even then, I believe Apple is an evil business, moreso than many other tech companies for one reason. No it's not their high prices. Actually it's worse than that. We can laugh all we want about the $1000 Studio Display stand but really, that's far from their worst. The real reason I hate Apple is because they manipulate the consumer.</p>
   <p>If your first reaction to this is "HOW" then Apple managed to do it on you too.</p>
   <p>So why is Apple evil? Apple is evil because they manipulate the consumer into thinking their products provide privacy for the normie (Which most Apple users are).</p>
   <p>Need a good example? Simply watch their newest (at the time of writing) video called Privacy on iPhone. In the video they in sort of a weird way claim Apple and iPhone devices specifically allow you to disable app tracking. So why is this evil? Isn't this great for privacy?</p>
   <p>If the normie consoomer who doesn't know any better tries to disable app tracking using whatever features Apple the evil company provides, Apple gets all that data for themselves. Now of course they claim they don't sell your data but how are you gonna know? Almost every piece of software written by Apple is ABSOLUTELY PROPRIETARY which means you have absolutely no idea what it does with all your data.</p>
   <p>And while they have access to your data, the normie consoomer thinks Apple cares about your privacy and only wants the best for you. This means people who are now starting to care about privacy go out and buy iPhone devices thinking they're good for privacy when they're really not.</p>
   <p>Sure, iPhones may be better than Samsung, Huawei, Xiaomi and the endless other companies when it comes to privacy but to think they don't track you is really stupid. A general rule is, if something's not "free and open source software" it tracks you. Apple stops other companies from tracking you but they track you themselves instead. At the end of the day, the data is still collected and sent to Apple so it really makes no difference in the end.</p>]]>
   </description>
</item>
<item>
   <title>Open source: Fake freedom.</title>
   <link>https://speedie.gq/post13.html</link>
   <guid>https://speedie.gq/post13.html</guid>
   <pubDate>Sun, 5 June 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
   <description>
   <![CDATA[<p>Yep, I'm back with yet another rant because we totally don't have enough of those yet. I hope the next few blog posts are going to be.. more positive but I feel like this must be said.</p>
<p>This one is about free software and open source. This is probably my first blog post that has made be.. extremely angry while writing it. In fact I had to edit the finished post 5 times just because I kept insulting the people who support 'open source'. So please..</p>
<p>Stop using the term 'Open Source'.</p>
<p>By supporting 'open source' you're not supporting software that respects the user's freedom. Instead you're supporting 'fake' freedom. Open source is just as evil as proprietary software. The only difference is that the source code for the application is public. You don't wanna support proprietary software with a nice mask on, do you?</p>
<p>If free software is what you <i>actually</i>support then please use the term 'Free software' or 'Libre software' instead. If you support 'open source' then you're supporting companies like Microsoft, Google, Apple and many more who don't care about your (free)dom but only the 'collaborate' aspect of open source.</p>
<p>They like open source because they get YOUR (as in people who write code for the project) work and code for nothing in return. Open source is important but it's just part of freedom.</p>
<p>In addition to this, many people who are unaware of the free software movement/project think these big tech companies are nice people who care about their users when this is far from the truth.</p>
<p>Open source does not guarantee the user's freedom. This is why tech companies support 'Open source' but not free software. Free software is evil to them because they want control, something free software doesn't and cannot allow.</p>]]>
   </description>
</item>
<item>
   <title>Why I switched license from MIT to GPLv3</title>
   <link>https://speedie.gq/post14.html</link>
   <guid>https://speedie.gq/post14.html</guid>
   <pubDate>Sun, 5 June 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
   <description>
   <![CDATA[<p>Like I said last time, I wanted to make some more positive blog posts so here goes, I guess!</p>
   <p>In this blog post I wanna sort of explain why I switched to the GNU GPLv3 license after having used the MIT license for such a long time. I also hope this will be my last FSF/GNU related post for a bit but usually I just write about whatever is on my mind.<p>
   <p>- So why did I switch license from MIT to the GPLv3?<p>
   <p>It's fairly simple. Both are free software licenses but the MIT license and most other licenses are missing one specific point that I really like and it's the main reason I switched.</p>
   <p>Most other licenses including the MIT allow anyone to fork the project and redistribute it just like the GPL but the problem is the license can be changed to whatever the fork author wants. This also includes a proprietary license which goes against what I want out of a license. I want to <i>prevent</i> non-free software, I don't want to <i>help</i> non-free software.</p>
   <p>- How are you helping non-free software?</p>
   <p>Essentially I'm writing their software for them, so then they can just fork it and make proprietary spyware out of it. This has happened to many different projects and you can thank these licenses that don't prevent a license change for proprietary firmware and other nasty stuff that (probably) runs on your GNU/Linux box. Some people may argue that the GPL is actually non-free because it <i>doesn't</i> let you fork under another license but I heavily disagree</p>
   <p>At first it may seem like that but as soon as someone forks your software and changes the license to a non-free license you have MORE proprietary spyware so in the end you're causing more problems than you're solving. The GPL essentially tries to end proprietary software by providing a license which guarantees freedom like I stated in my <a href="https://speedie.gq/post13">previous post.</a> which is something I support. So that begs the question. Should you switch to the GNU GPLv3 license?</p>
   <p>Now, I would like to add that if you're heavily against the GNU project or the Free Software Foundation due to Richard Stallman, then you probably do not want to use the GPL. And most of the time the people who choose to NOT use the GPL for this reason cannot actually find a justifiable reason for their choice. I don't know about you and it's not my decision but either way the GPL is just a <i>software license</i> and therefore it really doesn't matter who wrote it. Just know that by using a license that doesn't prevent/stop non-free software, you're making the world a worse place.</p>
   <p>If your goal in addition to providing users with freedom and a great piece of software then the GPL is probably for you. The GPLv3 license guarantees freedom for anyone who uses the software. Therefore <i>in my opinion</i> by using the GPLv3 license you are making the world a better place by stopping potential proprietary software.</p>
   <p>That's all for this blog post I guess, bye.</p>]]>
   </description>
</item>
<item>
   <title>Are GNU/Linux users elitist or are normies too stupid to learn?</title>
   <link>https://speedie.gq/post15.html</link>
   <guid>https://speedie.gq/post15.html</guid>
   <pubDate>Mon, 6 June 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
   <description>
   <![CDATA[<p>Another day another blog post!</p>
   <p>Windows/macOS users often call me an elitist GNU/Linux user but is that really deserved? Well, I personally don't think or care too much about people's opinions on me. After all, I have better things to do and since it's so common to call GNU/Linux users 'elitist', it doesn't really mean anything to me.</p>
   <p>However, since this is so common I wanted to find this out for myself. So let's think for a moment here? Why do I write blog posts just like the one you're reading?</p>
   <p>Well, for me it's because it allows me to say exactly what I think whenever I want. It's a nice way to (sometimes) express your anger at something. However I don't really view myself as an elitist. After all, I write blog posts like this one and write guides like <a href="https://speedie.gq/guide02.html">this one</a>. I went out of my way to help <i>new</i> GNU/Linux users in this case install Arch.</p>
   <p>If I was an elitist I'd tell you to 'RTFM' like every Arch user ever. Instead I went out of my way to help you get started with Arch.</p>
   <p>What I'm not about to do however is read the 'FM' for you. If you aren't capable of reading plain English then I will call you exactly what I view you as, <i>an idiot</i> or <i>a normie</i>.</p>
   <p>In addition to this, it ALWAYS seems like the people calling <i>me</i> an elitist are part of this group. People who will complain about something being difficult without having the patience to read and perform. They will call anyone who uses software that they view difficult to use (for example Gentoo, Arch, or suckless software) an elitist. They can't seem to find one reason why anyone would actually want to use said software except to look cool on the internet.</p>
   <p>Now I'm not gonna deny the fact that there do exist <i>some</i> elitist GNU/Linux users but they're the exception rather than the rule. Most people who use this (in the normie's eye difficult) software do it because it's more efficient once you know how it works. A good example of this would be Vim.</p>
   <p>The 'real' elitists (in my opinion) are the normies since they consider anyone who uses X software an elitist even if only a few (but loud) people have an elitist attitude about the software they use.</p>
   <p>The normies are proud to be normies. Just like we are proud to use this 'hard to use' software.</p>
   <p>The difference is, we try to teach the normies this 'hard to use' software but instead of actually learning anything, they simply call us elitists. Therefore, I personally consider the normies the actual elitists.</p>
   <p>To be clear, if you don't understand how to use X software then that's perfectly fine. What I do have a problem with is proud stupidity. Normies are always proud to be normies instead of learning. They take pride in being stupid.</p>
   <p>That's all for this blog post. Happy <i>pride</i> month too, I guess?</p>]]>
   </description>
</item>
<item>
   <title>Return of the rchat (rchat 1.0 is out)</title>
   <link>https://speedie.gq/post16.html</link>
   <guid>https://speedie.gq/post16.html</guid>
   <pubDate>Tue, 7 June 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
   <description>
   <![CDATA[<p>It's been a while since I've updated rchat. Earlier today I decided to improve rchat since I noticed it had many flaws that I thought I could improve on.</p>
  <p>rchat 1.0 brings many improvements. :help, :changelog and :history now have colors, Borders now scale based on the size of your terminal window.</p>
  <p>In addition to this, you can now use ~/.config/rchat/rchatrc to set options. This might be useful if you wanna set settings without using commands. You can also set the border character using the ':set sep' command. :help, :changelog and :donate commands can be used without joining now.</p>
  <p>You can reset all settings using the ':reset' command. You can also open my donation page by using the ':donate' command. Fairly small but very useful release. If you want to install it, you can clone the <a href="https://github.com/speediegq/rchat">rchat repository</a> and run <code>make install</code> as root.</p>
  <p>Gentoo and Arch repositories should be updated soon.</p>
  <p>Have a good day!</p>]]>
  </description>
</item>
<item>
   <title>Website update</title>
   <link>https://speedie.gq/post17.html</link>
   <guid>https://speedie.gq/post17.html</guid>
   <pubDate>Fri, 8 June 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
   <description>
   <![CDATA[<p>Since yesterday I've been working on a little website overhaul (mostly fixing errors and improving index.html) so this is just a quick blog post telling you about it.</p>
   <p>Normally I wouldn't make a blog post about small changes like this because... I mean it's a website, it's supposed to be updated and changed frequently.</p>
   <p>I've made some changes to the layout however and removed a few buttons. For example, my forks and dotfiles can now be found <a href="dotfiles.html">here</a> instead. This was done to keep the front page clean and to the point. I also removed some project links but they're still up, just in the <a href="projects.html">Projects</a> page instead.</p>
   <p>I added some fancy 90s style buttons as well to the footer of the front page because I thought they were cool. Let me know what you think about them and feel free to suggest more (License must be free to use). I also renamed a few blog posts but they're all still up. I plan on archiving a few blog posts but they won't be deleted.</p>
   <p>That's it for the website update. Thank you for reading and have a good day! Hopefully next blog post will be a little more useful! 😃</p>]]>
   </description>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
